Bonaventure Oblasser papers, 1901-1977 (bulk 1908-1950)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Papers of Bonaventure Oblasser, 1901-1977 (bulk 1908-1950)
MS 300
Bonaventure, Father, O.F.M., 1885-1967.
Consists chiefly of photocopies of Oblasser's correspondence, 1908-1950, which documents his efforts to secure the spiritual and financial needs of the Tohono O'Odham.
3.75 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Born in Portland, Oregon, on March 7, 1885, Emil Oblasser studied for the Franciscan priesthood (taking the name of Bonaventure) at Mission Santa Barbara from 1901 until 1908. After his ordination on June 28, 1908, his main assignments were:
1908-1910 St. Elizabeth Parish, Oakland, California
1910-1913 St. John's Mission, Komatke, Arizona
1913-1916 Mission San Xavier del Bac, Tucson, Arizona
1916-1922 Old San Solano, Cababi, Arizona
1922-1939 New San Solano, Topawa, Arizona
1939-1941 Mission San Luis Rey, California
1941-1948 Santa Isabel Indian Mission, California
His missionary work in Arizona resulted in the construction of over a dozen schools and churches on what would become known as the Papago Indian Reservation in southern Arizona. He was a member of the Committee that contributed to the formation of the reservation (1915), and he was a key advisor in both the legal battle against the Hunter Heirs in their claim to Papago Lands (1926) and in the formation of the tribal constitution (1936).
During his tenure, he gathered unique information on the Franciscan influence in Pimeria Alta, and collected censuses and other ethnological data on Indian populations. In the course of his research, he built a collection of books on the region which are now housed in the Oblasser Library at Mission San Xavier.
Father Oblasser celebrated the jubilee of his priesthood in 1958. He died in 1967 and was buried at Topawa cemetery.
Nicholas Perschl (1887-1969) was ordained a Franciscan in 1913. He spent many years at Mission San Xavier del Bac, and he worked amongst the Papago, Pima and Apache people in Arizona.
Organization
This collection is organized into two series:
Series I: Oblasser Papers, 1908-1977
Series II: Perschl Papers, 1901-1969
Scope and Content Note
These papers best document the activities of Bonaventure Oblasser in his daily struggles to secure the spiritual and financial needs of his missionary work to native peoples in California, and especially, Arizona. The bulk of the correspondence from 1908 to 1940 details his efforts to fund schools with supplies, furniture, and teachers, and to assist the Tohono O'odham (Papago) in shaping their geographical and political future. The correspondence covers the spectrum of his work, including topics such as: administering to the vast expanse of reservation; financing and constructing the buildings for religious and educational purposes; communicating with governmental officials and agencies on behalf of the Tohono O'odham on issues relating to the formation of the reservation, water, land and mineral rights; and assisting in the compilation of the tribal constitution.
There is also present some materials relating to censuses of various villages; Oblasser's annual reports to the Office of the Provincial on his accomplishments in the field; drafts of the Papago Constitution; his contributions to the erection of the Fray Marcos de Niza Monument near the Arizona-Mexico border; and many unpublished reports and articles that he wrote about Franciscan and Arizona history.
Correspondents in the collection include politicians Carl T. Hayden, George W. P. Hunt, Henry Ashhurst, government officials of the United States Bureau of Indian Affairs such as Charles Burke and John Collier; leaders of the Franciscan order and fellow missionaries in the field; support agencies for the missions such as the Bureau of Catholic Indian Missions, the Marquette League for Indian Welfare, and other private donors; scholars Herbert Bolton, Frank Lockwood, and others; and former students and friends.
The Subject Files contain correspondence, interviews, writings, and other records relating to various topics. Of interest are his missionary activities; a copy of Statuta Pro Missionibus: Ordinis Fratrum Minorum (1950), an interview (1959) of Oblasser by Bernard Fontana; censuses for the Saint John's Mission; and background information on San Jose Mission/Saint Nicholas Indian Center, and the San Xavier residence in Tucson. The largest folder of correspondence in these files relates to his work from 1956 to 1960 for the United States Department of Justice regarding the Papago Case Number 345 before the Indian Claims Commission for which he prepared an in-depth report on land tenure among the Papago Indians (however the report itself is lacking.)
The second subgroup of papers relate to the personal life and career of Nicholas Perschl. Included are excerpts from his diary and autobiographical writings for his early years as a missionary; general correspondence from 1901 to 1969, chiefly with other Franciscans, former students, and friends. and letters (in German) from members of his extended family in Austria.
Some materials in Latin, Spanish and German.
The original papers of Father Oblasser can be found at the Santa Barbara Mission Library, California.
Bonaventure, Father, O.F.M., 1885-1967 -- Archives; Perschl, Nicholas, 1887-1969 -- Archives; Hayden, Carl Trumbull, 1877-1972 -- Correspondence; Collier, John -- Correspondence; Hunt, George W. P. (George Wylie Paul), 1859-1934 -- Correspondence; Mission San Xavier del Bac (Tucson, Ariz.) -- History; Franciscans -- Missions -- Arizona; Catholic Church -- Missions -- Arizona; Missions -- Arizona -- History; Missionaries -- Arizona -- Archives; Tohono O'Odham Indians -- History; Tohono O'Odham Indians -- Government relations; Tohono O'Odham Indians -- Education; San Xavier Indian Reservation (Ariz.) -- History; Gila River Indian Reservation (Ariz.) -- History; Papago Indian Reservation (Ariz.) -- History; Correspondence; Oral histories; Reminiscences
Container List
- Series I: Oblasser Papers, 1908-1977
  - Correspondence, 1908-1962
    - Correspondence. 1908-1923 (Box 1, Folder 1-15)
    - Correspondence. 1924-1926 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
    - Correspondence. 1927-1933 (Box 3, Folder 1-9)
    - Correspondence. 1934-1937 (Box 4, Folder 1-9)
    - Correspondence. 1938-June 1941 (Box 5, Folder 1-8)
    - Correspondence. July 1941-May 1947 (Box 6, Folder 1-10)
    - Correspondence. June 1947-1951 (Box 7, Folder 1-8)
    - Correspondence. 1952-1962 (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
  - Subject Files, 1908-1977
    - Catholic Indian Outing Service. 1932-1933 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - "Cross Over the Desert." 1937 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Education: Pimeria Alta. 1956 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - "Franciscans Take Charge of Yuma, Arizona." ca. 1926 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - "Founding of Tucson." No Date (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Interview by Bernard Fontana. July 20-21, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Library of Piman Research. 1959-1962 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Miscellaneous. ca. 1942 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Missions/missionary activities. 1908-1952 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Mission Board. 1957-1961 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Prayers in Papago. (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Saint John's Mission Census. 1910-1912 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - San Jose Mission/Saint Nicholas Center (Tucson). 1977 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - San Xavier Historical Data. 1922 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - U. S. Department of Justice: Papago Tribe vs. U. S., Docket 345 Land Tenure Among the Papago. 1956-1960 (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Series II: Perschl Papers, 1901-1969
  - Biographical materials. ca. 1923-1930 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: General. 1901-1969 (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
  - Correspondence with Family in Vienna. ca. 1905-1948 (Box 9, Folder 4)